Master.
老师
There's some progress on another matter.
如今还有一事已有些眉目
If the Marquis of Wu'an
如若武安侯
truly is alive,
当真还活着
what should we do?
当如何
That will be a blessing for Great Yin.
那将是大胤之福
There are palace intrigues up ahead
前有宫廷内斗
and Prince Changxin's rebellion looming behind.
后有长信王叛乱
The Marquis of Wu'an is a pillar of stability.
武安侯就是一根定海神针哪
Father,
爹
Mother.
娘
Don't cry.
不哭了
Master, who is buried behind this nameless stele?
老师 这无字碑下所葬何人
Today is Father's birthday.
今日是爹的生辰
Let's be happy.
我们高兴些
That way, Father and Mother can be at peace
爹娘在天上看着
watching us from heaven.
才能安心
Fan Erniu. Meng Lihua.
樊二牛 孟梨花
Fan...
樊
Could they have been using another surname?
难道用的是另一个姓氏
The current situation is complicated.
眼下局势错综复杂
So much helplessness lies beneath.
背后隐藏着太多的无奈
When the time is right,
待时机成熟以后
I will tell you everything.
我会一一地告诉你
It's been 16 years.
十六年了
It's time for the truth to come to light.
真相是该大白于天下了
Zheng, burn the paper money.
姐夫 烧纸
There's still some paper money at home.
家里还有一些冥纸
When we get back, burn some for your parents too.
回去之后 你给你爹娘也烧一些
Does burning these things...
烧这些东西
really work?
真的有用吗
Of course.
当然
People burn paper money during festivals
人们逢年过节都烧纸
to tell their deceased loved ones
是为了告诉死去的亲人
that we still remember them.
我们还记得他们
Wenkan,
文槛
promise me one thing.
你要答应我一件事
If one day I'm gone,
倘若有一天我这把老骨头不在了
you must take good care of
你一定要替我照顾好
the two Fan sisters for me.
樊家的两姐妹
Never let them get involved.
千万不要让她们卷进来
Master, you are in such good health.
老师的身子骨这么好
Why say such things?
这是哪里的话
That day will come.
总有那么一天的
Promise me.
答应我
I promise you.
怀安谨记
Don't burn so much.
别烧那么多
Don't move.
别动
You two look just like Father and Mother.
姐夫和阿姐好像爹和娘
Thanks.
谢谢啊
You're welcome.
不谢
Come, Changning.
来 长宁
What's wrong with your wrist?
手腕怎么了
The ox cart tipped over when I was collecting pigs yesterday.
我昨日收猪时牛车翻了
I used my hand to break the fall
我用手去撑了一下
and sprained it.
就扭伤了
Changyu's wrist hurts often.
阿姐手腕经常疼
Butchering pigs is tiring work.
杀猪很累的
Constant strain on the wrist over the years can lead to tendon pain.
手腕常年用力会得筋痛症
Luckily the bone isn't affected.
好在没有伤到骨头
But you need to be careful from now on.
但你以后还是得注意保护
On the way back later,
一会儿回去路上
I'll get off at the grocery store to buy something.
我在杂货铺先下 买点东西
You don't have money, right? Here.
你没钱吧 给你点
No need. I have some.
不用 我有
How would you have money?
你怎会有钱
Get in the cart first.
先上车
Then you two go home first after I'm done shopping.
那一会儿买完你们就先回家
I'll go buy you some tangerine peel candy.
我去给你们买陈皮糖
Okay.
行
Changyu is the best.
阿姐最好了
You...
你
People keep dying
这左一番右一番地
in Xigu Lane.
在西固巷死人哪
Maybe we've provoked
也不知道招惹了什么
some kind of spirit.
不干净的东西
It's bad luck.
不吉利
Exactly.
就是
It seems this rice water isn't enough.
看来呀 这点淘米水是不够
In a moment,
一会儿啊
I need to find some dry mugwort leaves
我得找点干艾草的叶子
and hang them on this door.
看来挂在这门上才行
Exactly.
就是
Look at that jinx.
你看那丧门星样
She was actually staring at us.
还瞅呢
You're back?
回来啦
What's wrong?
你怎么了
You look listless.
没精打采的
Why are you all wet?
怎么湿乎乎的
The snow was deep. It must have been the snow.
路上雪深 沾湿的吧
Wait.
你等等
Was someone bullying you
是不是谁欺负你了
and saying bad things about you?
在那儿嚼舌头呢
Who dares to do that?
谁敢在我背后嚼舌头啊
I'd knock their teeth out.
我不把他牙打断
I'm going to change my clothes.
我去换衣服啊
Fan Changyu!
樊长玉
Come out here! Fan Changyu!
你给我出来 樊长玉
Fan Changyu! You...
樊长玉 你
Fan Changyu,
樊长玉
your sister pushed our Hutou
你妹妹晌午
down the stairs at noon.
把我们家虎头推下台阶
Look.
你看看
He lost two front teeth.
这门牙都摔缺了两颗
Tell me, what are you going to do about it?
你说说 该怎么办吧
My sister has always been weak.
我妹妹一向体弱
Your grandson is years older than her.
你这孙子又比她大好几岁
How could she possibly push him?
她怎么可能推得动他
Well...
这
Granny Kang, let's talk this over calmly.
康婆子 有事好好说
You're making a scene in front of the neighbors.
你在门口让 让街坊邻居看笑话
The Fan family bullied my grandson.
他们樊家欺负我孙子
Why should I be afraid of being laughed at?
我还怕别人笑话我啊 我
Isn't it normal for kids to have
小孩子打闹
a few bumps and scrapes when they're playing around?
磕磕绊绊这不是常有的事吗
-Stop shouting. -Whether you have the right
你别在这儿嚷嚷
to demand justice here or not,
这公道由不由得你讨
we need to ask Fan Changning first.
问问樊长宁再说
Changning, come out.
宁娘 出来
Come out. It's okay.
出来吧 没事
Changning, come here.
宁娘 你过来吧
Come.
来
Changyu wants to ask you something.
阿姐问你点话
Come here.
快过来
Come.
来
Let me ask you.
阿姐问你啊
Did you push Hutou?
有没有推虎头
Look at that.
你看看啊
Such a little child already knows how to lie.
这么小的孩子都会撒谎
She nodded just now,
刚才还点头呢
and now she's shaking her head.
这转眼就摇头
Fan Changning, I'm asking you.
樊长宁 我问你
Don't lie.
不许撒谎
Lying will make your mouth rot.
撒谎会烂嘴巴的
You know that?
知道吗
Get away!
你起开
How dare you push me!
你敢推我你
Is there no justice left?
这还有没有天理了
The Fan family is so arrogant!
他们樊家好大的气焰呀
They made my grandson like this,
把我孙子摔成这个样子
and... and she's acting as if she's completely in the right!
她 她还理直气壮起来了 你
Stop shouting!
你再嚷
Alright.
好了
See if I will shove your head
你看我会不会把你
into the swill bucket!
倒插进潲水缸里
I held back earlier
我刚才忍你
because I didn't know
那是因为我不知道
who my family had offended
我家惹了什么人
to bring trouble to Xigu Lane.
给西固巷带来了祸患
I feel guilty towards the neighbors,
我愧对乡亲们
but I haven't wronged you.
但不是对不起你
People keep dying in your family these days.
你们家这两天总是死人
Everyone in the lane knows that you jinxed them!
这整个巷子谁不知道是你克的呀
You and Mrs. Song gossip about me every day.
你和宋老婆子天天在背后编排我
Do you think I don't know?
以为我不知道吗
Fine.
好
I'll grant your wish today.
今天我就遂了你的愿
What are you doing?
你要干什么
The neighbors are watching.
这邻居们都在这儿看着呢
Do you dare commit violence here?
你要恃恶行凶不成
You've already ruined my reputation.
反正名声已经被你们编排得臭了
You don't think I still care
你不会以为我还在乎
what they think, do you?
他们怎么看吧
If I really do something to you,
要是我真动手
do you think they'll help you?
你觉得他们会帮你吗
Changning.
长宁
When I asked if you pushed Hutou just now,
阿姐刚刚问你有没有推虎头
why did you nod first and then shake your head?
你为何点头又摇头
I did push him.
我是推了他
But he was too fat.
但他太胖了
I couldn't move him.
我没推得动
He chased me,
他来追我
fell down the stairs himself,
自己从台阶上摔了下来
and broke his front teeth.
才把门牙给摔坏了
Hutou said you pushed him!
虎头说就是你推的
Shut up!
你闭嘴
I knew Hutou fell on his own.
我就说虎头他自己摔的
Why did you push him?
你为何推他呀
He pulled my hair,
他揪我头发
snatched my candy,
还抢我的糖
threw rice water on me,
还往我身上洒米水
and called me a jinx's sister,
说我是丧门星的妹妹
saying I needed a splash of water to get rid of my bad luck.
要泼水去晦气
You filthy old hag who deserves to be buried with no coffin!
你这个死了没棺材板的腌臜老货
Not only do you have a wicked tongue,
你自己嘴上不积德
you don't even do good deeds for your grandson.
你也不给你孙子积点德
Aren't you afraid the King of Hell
你也不怕以后见了阎王
will rip your tongue out after you die?
被钩了舌头
How am I wicked?
我怎么不积德了
Did I kill her parents?
她爹妈是我害死的吗
Did I kill all those people who died in her family?
他们家死的这些人都是我杀的吗
Everyone in Lin'an knows
咱们全林安 谁不知道
she's a jinx!
她就是个丧门星
Only you and your husband,
只有你和你们家老头
who have no one to bury you when you die,
两个没人送终的
took in this whole cursed family.
才巴巴地收留这灾星一家
Maybe one day,
说不定哪天呀
she'll bring you to your death too.
她也会把你克死的
If you ask me,
要我说呀
the Fan family
他们樊家呀
should've gotten out of Xigu Lane long ago.
早就应该滚出咱这西固巷
Who knows when their enemies will come looking for them.
说不定哪天仇人哪 就会来寻的
-Why are you so mean? -If I'm going to jinx anyone to death,
你嘴巴怎么这么毒
you'll be the first one, you old hag.
也先克死你这个老不死的
Why should I leave Xigu Lane?
要我滚出西固巷 凭什么
If you're so scared, you leave.
你那么怕 你自己滚啊
And listen—
还有
if you ever
你以后
lay a finger on Fan Changning again,
要再敢动樊长宁一根头发
whichever hand you use, I'll cut it off.
你哪只手动的我砍哪只手
You think I'm scared of you?
我还怕了你不行啊
Don't try to scare me.
你别吓唬我你
Scare you?
吓唬
I can chop a pig's trotter clean off with one stroke.
我猪肘子都能一刀砍断
Your hand would be even easier.
砍你的手更简单
Left or right?
左手右手
Which one do you want to keep?
你想留哪只啊
-How about neither? -Don't!
要不都别留了吧 别
Hutou!
虎头
Hu...
虎
Grandma!
奶奶
Karma!
现世报
This is instant karma!
这就是现世报
You saw that, right?
大家伙都看到了吧
Changyu and I didn't touch this old woman.
我跟长玉都没碰这老婆子
She fell on her own.
这老婆子自己摔的
It was her! She kicked me!
是她 是她踹的我
Granny Kang,
康婆子
we were all watching.
我们大家都看着呢
You fell on your own.
是你自己摔的
You must have been too vicious with your words,
定是你嘴上没个把门的
so heaven punished you.
这天都要收了你吧
Exactly.
就是
It was this jinx! She jinxed me!
是这个克星 是她克的我
Get lost! Or I'll jinx you to death!
赶紧滚 小心我把你克死
Granny Kang,
康婆子
be careful.
慢点
Or you may knock your teeth out.
小心磕掉自己的大牙
Don't blame Changyu for that too.
别再怪到长玉的身上去了
Changning.
长宁
in the future, if anyone bullies you outside,
以后在外面受了委屈
come back and tell me, alright?
回来跟阿姐讲 好不好
How about you...
要不然
not wait for the New Year?
别等过年了
Just go now.
你先走吧
Just because of a few words from others,
因着旁人几句话
you want to chase me away?
就想赶我走啊
My family's troubles
我家的祸事
have already dragged you in twice.
确实已经两次牵连到你了
You don't owe me anything anymore.
你也不欠我什么了
If you cut ties with us sooner,
与我家早些断干净
you'll be safer.
你能安全些
You believe that woman's words?
你信那妇人的话
No.
不信
I don't believe in fate,
我不信命
nor in that nonsense about being a cursed star
也不信什么天煞孤星
who brings misfortune.
命中带克的说法
I just think that those people
我只是觉得那些人
won't let my family go easily,
不会轻易放过我家
so I don't want to drag you down with us.
不想连累你
If you think you can push me away
你觉着为了我好
just because it's for my own good,
可以同我划清界限
then what about Changning?
那宁娘呢
Are you going to cut ties with her too?
你跟她也划清界限吗
I can't.
不行
She's too young.
她太小了
I have to keep her with me.
我得带着她
So,
所以
you're only driving me away, is that it?
只是赶我走是吧
You're not the type to take an insult lying down.
你也不是个逆来顺受的脾性
If someone splashes water on you,
被人泼了水
just teach them a lesson right then and there.
当场教训回去便是
There's a saying I once heard from Mr. Wang:
我听王叔说过一句话
"The law does not punish the masses."
法不责众
It means that if a large group of people breaks the law,
说是很多人犯了法
the authorities usually won't punish them all.
官府是不会惩罚所有人的
Now the whole town is gossiping about me
如今在背后议论我的
behind my back.
是整个镇子的人
I might be able to deal with one of them,
我训得了一个
but can I deal with them all?
训得了所有人吗
Then have you ever heard of the saying
那你听过一个词
"make an example of someone"?
叫杀鸡儆猴吗
Human nature is evil.
人性本恶
If you're weak and easy to bully,
你若软弱可欺
no matter how kind you are,
就算你再善良
no one will help you.
也没人能拉你一把
But if you rise to power,
但你若飞黄腾达了
even if you've done terrible things,
就算干了伤天害理之事
plenty of people will rush to flatter you.
也会有大帮子人上赶着巴结你
Superstitions are just meant to confuse people.
鬼神之说本就是迷惑人心的
Like the candy that hit Granny Kang just now—
就像砸向康婆子那颗糖
in her eyes,
在她看来
it was just a ghost playing tricks.
不过是鬼神在作怪罢了
You can say these things to me,
你可以同我说这些话
but if you start distancing yourself
但你若是因此
from Mr. Zhao and Mrs. Zhao because of it,
跟赵大叔赵大娘一家子疏远了
they will be heartbroken.
他们会难过的
Then take what I said earlier
那方才
as a moment of impulse.
就算我一时冲动
Please stay.
你留下来吧
So it's up to you
你想让我走就走
whether I leave or stay, huh?
想让我留就留啊
You've got some nerve.
你可真敢
Don't be mad.
你别生气嘛
The candy I bought you wasn't meant for that.
给你买的糖也不是那样用的
You should have gone and found some pebbles.
你去寻些小石头
Candy is expensive.
糖多贵啊
It was not worth it.
不划算
I never had the chance to ask before.
以前都没机会问你
Why did you become an armed escort and risk your life?
你为何要去当镖师玩命
Because...
因为
♪ The moon is as quiet as me ♪
我有不得不做的事情
Just like how
就像
you want to keep running your father's butcher shop.
你想继续开你父亲的肉铺一样
My father
我父亲
also had unfinished business.
也有未完成的事情
I want to finish it for him.
我想继续替他做下去
So your family ran an escort agency?
所以你家是开镖局的
And you were the Young Master?
你是镖局少东家
Rebuilding an escort agency costs a lot of money.
那重建镖局可要花好多钱呢
When I have some money to spare,
到时候手上富裕了
I can help you out.
可以资助你一些
No need.
不必了
I haven't repaid you
你当初的救命之恩
for saving my life yet.
我还没有回报你
That's a completely different matter.
这两码事
♪ I pray that our love will not be like sand ♪
之前 你同意入赘
we were already even.
我们就已经两清了
♪ To guard our love forever ♪
你想跟我两清
That's not what I meant.
我不是那意思
We've known each other for so long,
我俩认识这么久了
yet I still don't know when your birthday is.
还不知你的生辰是何时
My birthday is easy to remember.
我生辰可好记了
It's 2 days after the Lantern Festival.
元宵后两天
The holiday spirit is still strong then.
那时候年味还浓呢
It's very lively.
热热闹闹的
What do you want?
想要什么
I want my family all together,
想要一家人整整齐齐
safe and sound.
平平安安
And if in the spring,
若开春
I could keep another litter of piglets, that would be even better.
能再养一窝小猪就更好了
Your Majesty, I have a proposal.
臣有本启奏
Grand Tutor, please go ahead.
太傅请讲
Your Majesty,
陛下
the weather has been erratic this year.
今岁风雨失调
The land is barren, and the crops have failed.
赤地千里 禾黍不登
In this year of disaster,
今灾年之际
if we still transport grain to the front line,
若仍将存粮运往前线
I fear it will cause a refugee crisis
恐生流民之患
and shake the foundation of the state.
动摇社稷之基
Your Majesty, I implore you
臣恳请陛下
to revoke the restoration order for the front line.
收回前线的修整令
I humbly ask for Your Majesty's judgment.
请陛下圣裁
The situation on the front line changes rapidly.
这前线战事瞬息万变
Even the Marquis of Wu'an has fallen in battle.
连武安侯都已折戟沉沙于战场
Provisions before a great battle are of the utmost importance.
大战前的粮草乃是重中之重
How can we easily revoke the order?
怎能轻易收回
After years of war,
如今战乱多年
the treasury is now empty and cannot bear the burden.
国库早已空虚 实难重负
If the treasury is empty, levy grain locally
国库空虚 就就地征粮
to solve the urgent need.
以解燃眉之急
After we pacify Chongzhou,
等平定崇州之后
we can return it to the people.
再归还于百姓即可
It is deep winter now, and the end of the year is approaching.
如今正值隆冬 年关将至
The people's surplus grain is not enough to fill their own stomachs.
百姓的余粮尚不能果腹
Levying grain locally?
就地征粮
Prime Minister Wei,
魏相
are you not worried
您就不担心
that it will incite a civil uprising?
会激起民变吗
The front line is engulfed in flames of war,
前线烽火连天
and our soldiers are fighting bloody battles.
战士们浴血奋战
Provisions are the lifeline of the army.
粮草乃是军中的命脉
How can they go a day without them?
怎能一日无之
If the enemy takes this chance to march south and breach our cities,
若让敌人趁此机会南下破城
I fear it will bring disaster and ruin to our nation.
恐怕会引来灭国之灾
Grand Tutor,
太傅
do you dare to bear such a heavy responsibility alone?
敢凭一己来承担如此重责
Surely, Grand Tutor Li,
想必李太傅
you do not wish to repeat the tragedy of 16 years ago,
也不愿意重蹈这十六年前
when provisions failed to reach Jinzhou City,
瑾州城粮草未至
leading to its massacre?
被屠城的覆辙吧
Prime Minister Wei is farsighted.
魏相深谋远虑
He is truly the most loyal subject of Great Yin.
实乃我大胤第一忠臣是也
[Diligent and Virtuous]
魏相忠义
Uncle,
舅舅
when I grow up, I want to be like my father,
我长大了 要像我爹一样
fighting on the battlefield.
征战沙场
Prime Minister.
相爷
Come in.
进来
Prime Minister, please have some ginseng tea.
相爷请喝参茶
Have Zheng's remains
征儿的尸骨
still not been found?
还是没寻到吗
This child is of the Wei family's bloodline.
这孩子身上流着魏家的血
And he was raised with such care by you.
从小又受到相爷悉心的教养
They say a maternal uncle is like a second father.
都说娘亲舅大
It's such a pity that he died like this.
如此去了 实在是可惜
Please take care of yourself, Prime Minister.
还望相爷保重身体
-And Xuan... -Please go back.
宣儿那里
I spoke out of turn.
是妾身多嘴了
I beg your forgiveness, Prime Minister.
还望相爷海涵
I shall take my leave.
妾身告辞了
Prime Minister,
相爷
He Jingyuan, Governor of Jizhou,
霁州牧贺敬元
has sent a brocade box by fast horse.
快马送上一方锦盒
He has always been cautious.
他一向行事谨慎
To General Suituo,
致随拓将军
Jinzhou is in critical danger.
瑾州告急
I must return to the capital for an urgent matter.
吾蓄因急事返京
Therefore, I am sending my household general, Wei Qilin,
故遣家将魏氏祁林
to request immediate reinforcements with the Tiger Tally
持虎符求将军即刻发兵驰援
to resist Beijue together
共御北厥
and save Crown Prince Chengde.
解承德太子之困
General, Wei Yan.
中郎将 魏严
Eighth day of the fifth month, the 26th year of Taikang.
泰康二十六年 五月初八
It seems He Jingyuan
看来这贺敬元
is using his own life as leverage
是想以自己的性命相逼
to make me spare the two daughters of that traitor.
让我放过那两个叛主之徒的女儿
He Jingyuan is so bold.
这贺敬元大胆
Prime Minister, you shouldn't have been soft-hearted back then
相爷 您当年就不该心软
and stopped searching for Wei Qilin's body.
放弃寻找魏祁林的尸首
Zheng's
征儿
sudden investigation into the Jinzhou massacre
忽然调查瑾州惨案一事
must have been instigated by someone with ulterior motives.
定是有心之人在唆使
Now,
如今
even He Jingyuan goes against my orders.
就连贺敬元也不听话了
Why don't you let me
不如着属下
go and get rid of He Jingyuan?
去除了这贺敬元
The battle in Chongzhou is critical right now.
眼下这崇州之战焦灼
If I lose a weapon like He Jingyuan,
若是再折了贺敬元这把刀
the Northwest will be in peril.
西北之地岂不危矣
I see.
是
Forget it.
罢了
They are just two girls.
不就是两个女娃吗
Let them live.
留着吧
How much trouble can they possibly cause?
又能掀起多大的浪
Lord Li?
李大人
[Fill Your Belly]
你家夫婿今日不在家
He went out on business.
他出门办事去了
Do you need him for something, My Lord?
大人找他有事啊
Just asking casually.
随口一问
By the way,
对了
regarding the case involving your family,
你家之前的案情
I have figured out everything.
我已厘清所有
Who did it?
谁干的
The Qingzhou Government Office found that the attacks on your family
霁州府查到你家几次遇袭
stemmed from an escort mission your father undertook years ago.
缘于你父亲当年运送的一趟镖
Rumor has it that it involved a treasure map
传闻那是前朝皇室
left by the previous dynasty's royal family.
留下的一张藏宝图
Over a decade ago,
十几年前
everyone in the escort agency was killed.
整个镖局的人都被杀害了
Only your father survived.
唯有你父亲死里逃生
That was why he could settle down here in Lin'an Town all these years.
这才到林安镇安稳了这些年
After the turmoil in Chongzhou,
崇州战乱之后
the treasure map was brought up again.
藏宝图之事又被旧事重提
The bandits from Qingfeng Stronghold tracked down your father,
清风寨山匪查到你父亲的行踪
which is why they repeatedly attacked your home—
这才几次三番来你家行凶
to get that treasure map.
为的就是得到这张藏宝图
Treasure map?
藏宝图
I've never heard my parents mention it.
我从未听爹娘提起过
Yes.
是
So, rumors can be deadly.
所以 传言害人
Why did Li Huaian make up such a lie
为何李怀安要编这么个谎话
just to close the case?
为其结案
My parents...
我爹娘
died just because of a rumor?
就因为一句传言而丧命
A few days ago, the rebels in Chongzhou announced
数日前 崇州反贼发出消息
that they had already found the treasure map.
说他们已经找到了藏宝图
The Qingfeng Stronghold bandits won't come to town anymore.
清风寨山匪不会再来镇上了
You can rest assured.
你大可放心
If there's a chance to catch those bandits
若有机会抓到那群贼人
and let my parents rest in peace,
让我爹娘瞑目
I am at your command, My Lord.
我任凭大人吩咐
This is the relief fund sent
这是霁州牧贺大人体恤民情
concern for the people. He specially appointed me to deliver it.
特命本官送来的抚恤金
Is it all for me?
都给我的
For those who suffered at the hands of the Qingfeng Stronghold bandits
此番遭了清风寨山匪毒手的
and lost family members,
家里死了人的
the government has issued consolation money.
官府都发了抚恤金
It's not just your family.
不止你一家
The standard is 10 taels per person.
按例是一人十两
Here is 30 taels of silver.
这是三十两银子
Please accept it.
你收下吧
Dry weather!
天干物燥
Beware of fire!
小心火烛
It's flying over!
飞过来啦
Changyu,
阿姐
you talked in your sleep again last night.
你昨晚又说梦话了
What did I say?
说什么了
You said you were afraid the spices from out of town weren't authentic.
你梦里说怕是外地香料不正宗
You said,
说什么
"Five spices aren't enough, we need six."
五香不够 得加六香
Then you said that if Zheng left,
然后 你说姐夫走了
you'd never find such a handsome husband again.
就再也找不到这么好看的夫婿了
Keep your voice down.
你小声点
Changyu,
阿姐
we don't have to move anymore?
我们如今不用搬啦
But I already told the others in the village
可我已经跟村子里的其他人说了
that we were moving.
我们要搬
It's so embarrassing not to move now.
现在不搬 多丢人
Can we move out for a little while,
我们能不能搬一会儿
then move back?
再搬回来
That would count as moving.
就算搬过啦
Why are you so smart?
你怎么这么聪明啊
How about this?
你这样
Tell them
你跟他们说
we don't have to move anymore,
我们如今不用搬了
and give them some candy.
然后给他们一些糖
Then they won't laugh at you.
他们就不会笑话你了
Changyu,
阿姐
when will you go back to sleep with Zheng?
你什么时候回去跟姐夫睡啊
You're squeezing into my small bed every day.
每天挤我这小床
It's hard for me to even turn over.
我翻身都难
Mrs. Zhao says
大娘说
that a husband and wife should sleep together for life.
夫妻俩要一起睡一辈子的
What?
怎么
Are you sick of me already?
现在就开始嫌弃我了
I don't care.
我不管
I want to sleep with you.
我要跟你一起睡
For a lifetime!
睡一辈子
How dare you be sick of me!
让你嫌弃我
Are you still sick of me?
还嫌不嫌弃我
-No! -Are you?
不嫌弃了
You're not, are you?
不嫌弃了吧
I yield.
求饶了
Beg for mercy, quickly!
快点求饶
Changyu!
阿姐
All you do is eat.
就知道吃
You're getting so fat.
吃这么胖
I wonder if you can still fly.
不知道还能不能飞得起来
Go now.
去吧
Morning, Mrs. Fan.
樊娘子 早
Morning.
早
Lord Li?
李大人
Why are you at the Song's house?
你怎么在宋家呀
I rented a vacant house from a broker.
我从牙人处租了一间空宅
When I got here, I realized it was opposite your home.
来这儿一看发现是你家对面
So this family is named Song?
原来这家人姓宋啊
Aren't you going back to Jizhou?
你不准备回霁州了
I promised I would find
我答应过我会找到
the murderer of your parents.
杀害你父母的凶手
I must keep my word.
当言出必行
Lord Li?
李大人
To catch the murderer, Lord Li
李大人为了抓到凶手
decided to stay for a while.
决定暂时住下来了
And he even rented Song Yan's house.
还租到了宋砚家的房子
Isn't that a coincidence?
你说巧不巧
What a coincidence indeed.
还真巧啊
I won't disturb you two.
不打扰二位了
What's wrong?
怎么了
The falcon is gone.
隼隼不见了
Maybe the lid wasn't closed tightly last night.
可能是昨夜盖子没盖好
After its wings healed, it flew away on its own.
它翅膀养好之后 自己就飞走了
This falcon has parents of its own.
这隼是隼的爹娘生的
It needs to go home to find them.
它也要回家找爹娘啊
Don't cry.
不哭了
There's nothing we can do.
没办法的嘛
The falcon has a family too.
那隼隼也有自己的家人啊
Don't cry.
不哭了啊
It will fly back.
会再飞回来的
Can you pinky-promise me for the falcon?
姐夫能替隼隼跟我拉钩吗
You're going to leave sooner or later,
你早晚要走的
aren't you?
对吗
In my current situation,
我现在的处境
loving someone
喜欢上谁
only puts them in danger.
便是害谁
People
这人啊
are not deities who cut off emotions and desires.
并非斩断七情六欲的神仙
It's hard to control
心动之事
your feelings.
难以自控
Don't coax her.
你别哄她了
Changning is just a bit lonely.
宁娘只是有些孤单
I'll buy a cage of chicks in the spring.
等开春之后我买一笼小鸡
With new playmates, she'll forget the falcon.
她有了新的玩伴就不记得那隼了
In the spring,
等开春之后
I'll buy you a big cage of chicks, okay?
姐姐给你买一大笼小鸡好不好
No. I want the falcon.
不要 我就要隼隼
You don't want that?
你不要
I wasn't coaxing her.
我没哄她
To fully tame a falcon,
这鹰隼训到最后
you have to let it fly first.
就得先放飞的
Only one that returns
会飞回来的鹰隼
is truly tamed.
才是完全被驯服的鹰隼
But there's no guarantee it will come back.
那不是不一定回得来吗
So you're really not leaving Lin'an?
你真的不离开林安了
I was so happy when I heard the news
我听到这个消息
that I couldn't sleep all night.
高兴得一整晚没睡
I'll show you something.
我带你去瞧个物什
I've been preparing it for a long time.
我准备了好久呢
-Come on. -What is it?
来 什 什么物什呀
What are you doing?
干吗呢
Look.
你看
The auspicious time has arrived!
吉时到
Bravo!
好
Pray to the God of Wealth,
拜财神爷
and may your business prosper!
保你开张赚大钱
What's wrong?
怎么了
Nothing.
没事
Let's offer the incense.
上香吧
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
好
What would you like to eat?
要吃点什么
Your meat smells delicious.
你们家肉真香
I want a piece that's not too fatty.
我要块不腻的
None of them is too fatty. They're all good.
都不腻 都好吃
Pick a big one.
挑块大的
Okay.
好
I'll weigh it for you.
给您称啊
Come back often.
以后常来
Okay.
好
Changyu?
樊家丫头啊
It's me, it's me.
是我是我
Your shop has been closed for a while.
你家铺子有些时日没开张了
We couldn't buy braised meat anywhere.
害得我们都没地方买卤肉了
Turns out you came to Yixiang Restaurant to make it.
原来你是来溢香楼做卤肉啦
Mrs. Fan
樊娘子
is partnering with Yixiang Restaurant now.
如今和我们溢香楼合作
She'll sell exclusively here from now on.
以后啊 就在此处专卖
Ma'am, feel free to come by anytime if you like it.
婶子要是爱吃就请常来
Changyu's pork used to come
之前啊 长玉丫头的猪肉
with free offal.
都是送下水的
Then I won't be polite.
那我就不客气了
Look at this.
您看看这个
I... this...
我 这
This time...
这次
Well, this time...
不是 这次
Changyu's braised meat
长玉以前做的卤肉啊
used to be home-style.
都是家常味的
Now that she's with Yixiang Restaurant,
如今和我们溢香楼合作
the ingredients and recipe are upgraded.
这原料 调味 秘方都做了升级
Let alone offal,
别说是下水了
even the stock is pricier.
就连卤汤都比从前金贵不少呢
Well,
这样
then how can we common folk afford that?
我们老百姓哪吃得起呀
Forget it.
算了算了
I'll look elsewhere.
我还是去别家看看吧
We are opening today,
今日我们开业呀
so we want to start on a lucky note.
图个好彩头
If you
要是婶子以后
can bring us 5 customers in the future,
帮我们拉来五个顾客
you'll get a 20 percent discount.
取八扣之数
25 percent off for 10 customers.
十个七五扣
And 30 percent off for 20. How about that?
二十个七扣 如何
Alright.
行了
Changyu,
那长玉丫头啊
pick two good pieces of meat for me.
你帮我选两块好肉
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
今天呀 是老头子生日
Okay.
好嘞
I guarantee it'll be delicious and generous.
保证香喷喷 量足足
That piece.
那块吧
I didn't want to offer free offal before,
我之前不想送
and the customers were unwilling to accept it.
主顾们都不乐意
You just said a few words,
你动动嘴皮子
and they rushed to give us money.
他们就上赶着送钱
Qianqian, you're really amazing at doing business.
浅姐 你做生意可真了不得
Undercutting isn't business.
压价不算买卖
Mutual benefit is what business is all about.
互利才是生意嘛
The great man is he who is in harmony,
夫大人者
in his attributes, with heaven and earth;
与天地合其德
in his brightness, with the sun and moon;
与日月合其明
in his orderly procedure, with the four seasons;
与四时合其序
and in his relation to what is fortunate and what is calamitous,
与鬼神合其吉凶
He naturally—
先天
Your Lordship honors me with your presence.
侯爷大驾光临
My wait was not in vain.
下官就算没有白等
Tell me. What is your purpose in coming to the Fan family?
说吧 你来樊家有何目的
I came to the Fan family
来樊家
only to see you, Your Lordship.
只为了见侯爷
We have known each other since childhood
你我年幼便相识
and both learned martial arts from General He.
武艺皆学于贺将军
Since the conflict between the Li and Wei,
自从李魏相争
we've been avoiding each other.
你我二人便避而不见
It has been
这一晃
over a decade, hasn't it?
有十几年了吧
I am curious now.
我如今倒是好奇
Are you a Li
你是姓李
or a Wei?
还是姓魏
I only serve Great Yin
我只为大胤
and the people.
为百姓
What about you, Your Lordship?
那侯爷呢
Which side are you on now?
现在站哪方
Anyone can say
漂亮话
pretty words.
谁都会说
I have always
本侯一向
only served myself.
只为自己
The conflict between Li and Wei has become chaotic.
李魏之争已成乱局
And you intend to establish your own faction in the future.
往后侯爷还想自立门户
Do you wish to make this chaos even worse?
莫非是想将这乱局搅得更乱些